Karthikeyan Natarajan

SENIOR TECHNICAL PROGRAM MANAGER

4616 United Ln, Plano, TX 75024 • Phone: 214-801-2984

E-mail: KarthikNatarajanMBA@gmail.com • LinkedIn: http://www.linkedin.com/in/KarthikNatarajanMBA

Overcome complex business and Technical challenges... Salvage and strengthen relationships.

Rescue bottlenecked, behind schedule, financially off-track projects... Lead teams to achieve exceptional results

PROFILE SUMMARY

A successful Technical Program Manager who gets results that matter and who has a track record of leading multiple teams who have constantly delivered outstanding results. A multi-skilled, multi-faceted and experienced leader who is able to bring a fresh perspective to existing operations. Possess the vision needed to see the most challenging, exciting and inspiring possibilities clearly. Skilled strategist who transforms strategic plans into workable solutions and benchmarks performance against key operational targets/goals.

COMPETENT SKILLS

Program/Project Management • Delivery Transformation • DevOps • Agile Coaching • IT Strategy • Recruiting Distributed Team Management • Portfolio Management • Cross Functional Team Leadership • People Development Global Client Management • Vendor Management • Business Process Improvement • Software Development Business Analysis • Integration • Leadership • Quality Management • Strategic Communication • Costing & Budgeting • Conflict Management • Strategic Planning • Risk Management • Forecasting • Customer Service • Servant Leadership • Consulting • Negotiation • Mentoring • Scrum • Team Building • Team Leadership • Management • Agile Methodologies • Requirement Analysis • Software Development Life Cycle (SDLC) • IT Management • Personnel Management • Energy & Utility • Manufacturing • Financial Services

Key competencies include

IT Portfolio and Program management • Technical product management • Digital strategy • Delivery

Transformation • DevOps • Agile Transformation • Customer experience • Change management • Engagement

management, and Service delivery.

Tools

MS Project, Planview, Rally, JIRA, AgileZen, SharePoint, MS Office Suite, Visio, HP ALM, Quality center

Technologies and Products

C++, Java / J2EE, JavaScript, Angular, IBM Bluemix, Amazon Web Services (AWS), Machine Learning (ML), TensorFlow2.0, Python, VBScript, CSS, HTML, XML, PL/SQL, IBM Bluemix, Selenium, SoapUI, REST, AppDynamics, Splunk, Swagger

PROFESSIONAL WORK EXPERIENCE

SOFTWARE GUIDANCE & ASSISTANCE, INC., TARRYTOWN, NY

Aug. 2019 - Present

Sr. Technical Program Manager Client: Citi, Irving, TX

Aug. 2019 - Present

- Led multiple strategic Digital Transformation programs in Citi Consumer Banking business
- Managed global team of 15 developers in developing and delivering new products, features and programs
- Worked closely with Customer User Experience and Business teams to develop Product Vision and Roadmap for Product strategy implementation
- Monitored and tracked program execution to success by removing blockers and helped team to find the path forward in challenging situations

- Handled multiple contending priorities simultaneously in an exciting environment
- Leads directly, and through others, the creation of new initiatives such as Single SPA and implementation of Client-Side rendering (CSR) application
- Developed and managed project governance plans, project schedules, team goals, defining success criteria, project milestones, and budgets
- Managed Negotiation and conflict resolution, with both external and internal stakeholder
- Establish and practice Design thinking, LEAN and AGILE principles to deliver MVP product
- Define and track KPIs for product success and track data for opportunity identification
- Managed cross functional dependencies across business and IT teams including safety, security, regulatory requirements for IT applications
- Hired and developed the talents both within team and across organization
- Worked with technical team, vendor and partners to finalize technical design for solution
- Worked with dev team, QA team to implement BDD based testing and automation like CICD for quicker delivery

AMERICAN AIRLINES, FORT WORTH, TX

Oct. 2015 - Aug. 2019

IT Portfolio Manager

Feb. 2018 - Aug. 2019

- Managed Cobrand partnership program following DevOps CI/CD principles and using IBM Bluemix Cloud technology across multiple digital channels - Web, Mobile web, Mobile Apps (iOS & Android)
- Helped team to transition from Project to Product Model
- Motivated, encouraged and empowered high performance team to maximize and improve performance.
- Act as the trusted "technical" advisor and "go to person" for the stakeholders for business process improvement, innovation and supporting technologies.
- Created Program/Product roadmaps, directed work/projects, controlled cost/schedule elements, management of resources, communications management, reporting, and change management.
- Managed release timelines and communicated with management staff and clients to ensure progress satisfactorily; enacted delivery upon completion of MVPs and ensured that delivery adheres to Agile/DevOps practices maintained by the company

Technical Project Manager

Oct. 2015 - Feb. 2018

- Successfully managed, mentored, and trained cross functional Agile teams and executed multiple complex Web Development & Infrastructure projects from inception to completion within time and budgetary constraints.
- Demonstrated leadership capabilities, with ability to build strong consensus and achieve results through others.
- Coached teams on Agile values and principles by introducing Agile best practices such as time-boxing, continuous integration, code/design reviews, transparency, accountability, rally tracking, product visioning, technical debt reduction, self-management, empowerment and role training resulting in realized velocity improvement of more than 100%.
- Successfully led and helped project teams with the transition during American Airlines & US Airways merger in 2013 – 2017.
- Facilitated Agile Monthly Breakfast training sessions for the AA.com group of 100 folks in 2 different locations
 DFW and Phoenix every month to coach and enhance agile culture in our department.
- Worked closely with external vendors such as Google ITA, Switchfly to deliver exceptional service and established effective working relationships.
- Drove simplification, optimization, and quality of IT systems and processes through better stakeholder engagement, project requirements gathering and effective project.

Agile Project Manager | Scrum Master

Oct 2011 - Sep 2015

Client: American Airlines

- Managed multiple medium to large sized Web development and Infrastructure projects (\$1-6 Million USD)
- Served and helped cross functional team across multiple projects in a matrix environment to successfully develop and deliver quality code.
- Managed an effort to upgrade Content Management System (CMS) and migrate its corresponding repository to the new taxonomy & roll up structure which helped to cut down 50% of Content editors time.
- Managed projects using Agile Lifecycle Management (ALM) tools like Rally, AgileZen, Version One, etc.
- Introduced & taught Scrum, functional testing, performance testing, test case management & product backlog management.
- Managed wing to wing execution, issue resolution, program risks, and resource allocation and vendor relationship for product lifecycle management platform.

Technology Engagement Manager

May 2011 - Oct 2011

Client: Harley Davidson Financial Services

- Managed client expectations and ensured customer satisfaction through outstanding communication regarding project scope, schedule, and direction.
- Worked closely with H-D and Vendor development teams to define business requirements, identify and manage dependencies, plan and schedule project delivery dates to reduce bottlenecks.
- Identified and managed Risks and Issues and maintained smooth execution of the Project
- Responsible for time and cost management and reporting of Earned Value Management to Senior Management team,

COGNIZANT TECH SOLUTIONS US CORP.

Apr 2007 - Apr 2011

Associate | Technical Project Lead | Technical Project Manager Client: PepsiCo

Oct 2008 - Apr 2011

- Lead a team of over 12 analysts (on-shore and off-shore) across multiple projects and delivered projects successfully exceeding clients expectation; worked closely with the Business and IT as an application subject matter expert.
- Collaborated with Client Project Managers to develop estimates, plan, project schedules and resource allocation models while ensuring conformance to established project management process and methodology.
- Identified and facilitated conflict resolution within and outside the project teams.
- Managed client expectation and communicated the status of project throughout all phases; including completed tasks, pending deliverable, and outstanding items.

Programmer Analyst | Technical Project Lead

Apr 2007 - Oct 2008

Client: Alliance Data

- Led a team of 5 for providing testing services for various development efforts.
- Led QA practices such as project plan development, test strategy development, test plan development, test case & test data review.
- Worked closely with QA Analysts and Developers to develop test automation solution using HP Quick Test Professional (QTP).

COGNIZANT TECHNOLOGY SOLUTIONS INDIA PVT. LIMITED, CHENNAI, INDIA

Aug 2005 – Apr 2007

Programmer Analyst | Technical Project Lead

Jan 2007 – Mar 2007

Client: British American Tobacco, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia

- Led the project in upgrading the Handheld POS application and improving Mobile POS to Order Management workflow.
- Led business and system requirement gathering and performed Gap Analysis at code and data level such as data mapping and data conversion analysis.
- Analyzed existing workflows and developed new E2E business workflows from Mobile POS System to Order Management, Warehouse Management and Reporting Systems.
- Involved in hands-on Mobile Device, Database, ETL and Reporting Testing using PL/SQL & Oracle database;
 conducted User Acceptance Testing with business users.
- Lead multiple product development teams to ensure they deliver programs that achieve project success criteria, product cost, project budget and schedule.

Offshore Team Lead Aug 2005 – Dec 2006

Clients: Mitsubishi, 3M & Centrica Plc.

- Lead the team of 6-9 people and provided testing services to various clients
- Established SQA standards, technologies, and approaches for various projects
- Trained and mentored new team members; worked closely with cross-functional organizations, project teams, and clients to develop project estimates, schedules, and managed project delivery
- Helped to develop new testing automation framework, this was later utilized across various projects

EDUCATION

MBA - Innovation & Entrepreneurship THE UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT DALLAS, RICHARDSON, TX	Aug 2013 - May 2015
Bachelors in Electronics & Communication Engineering ANNA UNIVERSITY, CHENNAI, INDIA	Aug 2001 - May 2005
CERTIFICATION	

PMI-Certified Project Management Professional (PMP) Scrum Alliance Certified Scrum Master (CSM) AWS Certified Solutions Architect – Associate	Mar 2013 Dec 2012 Jul 2019
Computational Thinking for Problem Solving (Penn Engineering) ICAgile Certified Professional in Agile Coaching (ICP-ACC) ICAgile Certified Professional in Agile Team Facilitation (ICP-ATF)	Apr 2020 Apr 2015 Nov 2015
Business System Analysis & Business Process Management Basic Supply Chain Management	Mar 2013 Mar 2006

REFERENCE

Available upon request